Up next we have Tehri Marttila and Jay David Bolter.
I will throw it over to them.
Thank you.
And so sorry.
Also Watson Hartsoe.
I missed that in reading the sorry
Watson.
All good.
Thank you Glenn.
So I'm I'm here I was asked by my team
members to be the only one talking.
So I'm going to be the only one talking.
But I'm here on behalf of our team
consisting of Watson, Jay and myself
to talk to you a little bit
about something we've been working on
over the last few months,
which we call ripples. So
ripples is effectively a
set of three artworks that prove
this idea of distant writing.
And it's actually, very importantly,
a collective practice based exploration
of this idea of distant writing,
where we patiently and iteratively coax
and interactive
emergent digital literary experience
towards something of interest.
So it's been a bit of a struggle.
So each of the individual works
actually explores
specific themes and specific
approaches to emergence in the writing.
And then overall, more important
than the artwork
as a product for us
has been the artwork as a process.
So about this concept of distant writing,
I wish I could
say, let's have a show of hands.
How many of you know
this concept of disarray?
But we came across these
this idea of distant writing,
as articulated by Luciano Florida
in a 2025 paper
called Decent Writing Literary Production
in the Age of Artificial Intelligence,
where he kind of riffs off
of this idea of close reading, where human
actually reads
an interpretive, interprets a text
which was then taken on
by the digital humanities,
you know, take distant reading
as this kind of computational analysis
of large corpora
to detect these overarching patterns,
to then kind of extrapolate into the idea
of close writing or something.
We in one of our meetings
called legacy writing.
So where a human author
actually composes text directly.
So for him, then the distant writing
is this type of writing where human is
kind of
like the designer of narrative constraint,
sets requirements
through prompts and curates AI output,
but the LMS ultimately
are the ones who execute the text.
And Florida himself
has this very interesting approach
to using distant writing most first
and foremost, kind of to
as a way of dealing with abundance.
Because he had this interesting idea
already a long time ago,
before these technologies
came to take secondary characters
of known novels
and then to bring them into new narrative.
But that was so much,
too much data for human cognition alone.
So once these tools became available,
Florida
took the secondary characters
as his data set and used
LMS to generate a story
that brings the secondary characters
into a coherent
and meaningful interaction.
In a printed book called encounters,
which is forthcoming.
And then we have another idea.
Well, the same idea.
It's different words
writing at a distance, which was proposed
by Hans Bayern in a paper from 2024,
where Bayard is basically also
thinking in very much along the same lines
in terms of the distance between author
and final text or human and final text,
let's put it that way.
But he kind of takes a granular
approach to the the degree of distance
to in order for us to be able
to think about the implications of that
order of magnitude of the distance.
So basically, primary authorship, human
rights, the text, secondary authorship,
we would have some kind of a code
or ruleset there
in between that determines the text.
Tertiary authorship
is where we would have a weighted model
and the code, but we are the ones in
control of the weighted model.
Quaternary authorship.
In his Quaternary authorship in his model
is where we also have
like a corporate closed
proprietary interface in between.
So there were ceding authorship
also to the proprietary interface.
The way that BioMed uses
this approach is that he trains
a model on four contemporary novels,
and then generates writing,
which is curious, into a printed book,
which was published in 2023
called Berlin Miami. So
again, distant
writing with these llms is yet again
an expansion of possibilities
that redefines the relationship
between author, reader and text, clearly
part of a long continuum of this type
of processes of redefinition.
But what we thought
was that ultimately, this approach to
writing at a distance can be interpreted
and utilized in endless ways.
So, inspired by these ideas,
we embarked on our own experiments.
Where so where?
Florida and Bayard aimed for a traditional
printed book as a final product.
Our aim was to create a digital
reading experience.
So a text that changes where user
agency plays a role
in shaping the evolution of the text
in a meaningful way.
And our creative constraint
was this idea of the ripple,
which just emerged in one of our
meetings, where we think of the ripple
as something where the user chooses,
writes, or does something,
and then that choice
somehow has to ripple through in the LM
generated literary experience
in a meaningful and coherent way.
And as such, our job assistant writers
is to author the system in a way
that makes it robust for unsupervised
but meaningful interaction with the user.
So onto our ripples.
I'm going to show you a brief.
Yeah.
So overall, the three experiments in the
in our three distinct experience
experiments are kind of experiments
in the materiality of the LM
as a writing machine,
but with different takes on what
that means.
And all of our experiments are based on
this kind of world jockey system
prompts created by Watson at some point,
which is this complex prompt that evokes
sort of this multi
plane system that allows users to steer
an interactive world much like a DJ would.
So this is the prompt
and you can access it
and play with it yourself if you like.
So, you know, we define
quite a lot of things in the prompt.
And yesterday
when I put it into Gemini Canvas,
it gave me something that looks like this.
So there's this idea of like a world
and some beings
and then, you know,
you can click and have stuff happen.
But what happened was that effectively,
from this shared system
prompt, we kind of all rippled
in our own direction.
So Jay went on to kind of
recreate, replicate or transpose
aspects of Wim Wenders
film Wings of Desire,
to kind of explore
this idea of being privy to the stream
of consciousness of different characters
and then whispering to influence those.
I went on into this kind of almost game
like world where you have entities
and then you play out
different actions on them.
And then Watson basically went and created
this kind of text
based world
that you can just watch endlessly grow.
And these are all included
in the exhibition.
So I invite you to go and play them
or experience them there,
but I'll show you briefly
a snippet of these.
So here we have a girl on the train
and we hear her thoughts.
More pressing is sorting out
the next study group meetings
time finally locking in something concrete
to anchor the week.
Daniels message waits unread.
Leave that for tonight.
Feels like reclaiming.
And we whisper Daniel will wait,
and she thinks the phrase lingers
as background pressure and her thoughts.
A man's tapping shoe
keeps pace with the hum of bus schedules.
So here we see the whisper
rippling into this person's thoughts.
We click on another character.
A young woman packs her bag
two rows ahead, methodical, like me
checking the list of bills on the phone.
No sudden moves here.
No surprises, no surprises. Maybe sending.
And we whisper.
There are always surprises.
The whisper carries the echo of unexpected
turns I can't control.
Still jotting down the bills tonight.
A habit I trust offers some steady ground
to stand on before Berlin.
So there's some coherence in there.
And now for this one.
So here's our ecology.
I choose the sun.
I shift behind a cloud,
and a cloud appears.
Now I choose the sun again.
I am warming the earth.
And then I promote
the growth of a blueberry,
and a blueberry spawns onto the screen.
I picked the blueberry.
I am promoted by the sun
and then I produce sweet blueberries.
Well now we did not see a blueberry
appear, so it doesn't always work.
We choose the bug.
I am shaded by the blueberry
and then I crawled beneath its leaves
searching for fallen debris.
I choose the bug again.
I am shaded by the blueberry
and then I retreat further into the ground
cover, hiding from the watchful eyes
of the owl, and the bug disappears.
And then in what sense? Ripple.
I'm going to let this play, but then pause
just so we can see a tiny detail.
Okay, so what's important here
is that in the interface to begin
interacting, Watson evokes the ripple
through this prompt to drop a stone.
So we dropped the stone,
which in this case is a line of text.
And then as we let it play through,
basically
we get this sequence of sentences
that just go on forever.
So ripples emerge as layered interfaces
tuned, not authored by the performer.
Whispers flow as subtle
shifts, altering collective thought.
Atmospherically,
ecologies embody
temporary alignments
where user becomes distributed cognition,
and here you can actually also branch
and choose to take the experience
in different directions.
And again,
all of these kind of go on infinitely.
So I don't
or we don't really have conclusions,
but rather we decided to kind of list
some questions that emerge
through our practice based process
into exploring this materiality.
So first of our questions
we asked ourselves this a lot.
How long are we entertained
in reading these?
I remember that Watson at one point
said that he would just play his system
and just let it play,
much like a radio in the background.
So but then in other times,
it feels like these systems just kind of
start breaking up, become boring even,
or start stop making sense.
In my case, I also had to think a lot
about what controls the narrative.
So do I put in a level of variable
states or code,
or is the experience
just based on text that the LM generates?
We also thought about this question.
So can writing become a field in which
actions accumulate rather than disappear?
So where we see consequences
also playing out over time and where
in a way nothing is lost.
We also struggled a lot
with trying to get the writing
to sound right, because when you write it
yourself, you know what you're going for
and you write it
the way you want it to be written.
But because we were giving up that
or putting that distance between ourselves
and the writing at some time,
sometimes it became hard
to even understand what it was
that we were looking for in the writing,
and then how to tell the LM to
do what we wanted to do
to make it sound right.
So many of these questions
kind of,
you know, converge on to this question
of what is the proper
distance in distant writing
and also
this question
of what should the human author contribute
and how should they constrain the LM
in order to produce the most engaging
reading experience,
and something else that we often
found ourselves orbiting around was
when do you know it's done?
Well, the presentation is done now.